Mattia Amadio

Climate scientist and disaster risk expert

I am a environmental scientist with 10 years of experience in the field of climate hazards and disaster risk management. I have been involved in academic research projects globally, working with highly-ranked international institutions. In 2010 I was awarded a PhD in Science and Management of Climate Change from the Ca' Foscari University of Venice. Since 2012 I work as consultant for the World Bank's GFDRR. My expertise covers GIS analytics and mapping, impact modelling, and development of geodata tools. I am a science enthusiast with a sceptical attitude.





+39 3488441401

Venice, Italy

bit.ly/disasterologist

WORK EXPERIENCE

Short-term consultant

GFDRR, World Bank

11/2018 - Present

Washington DC (US)

- Data and process management for ThinkHazard! and GFDRR GeoNode
- o Risk Data Library design and development
- Support for disaster risk assessment in regional projects
- GIS data management and analytics
- Climate indicators for DRR

Contact: Pierre Chrzanowski

Researcher

Euro-Mediterranean Centre on Climate Change (CMCC)

Research foundation on climate change

03/2012 - 12/2020

Venice (IT)

- Climate-KIC project SAFERPLACES, flash-flood hazard from extreme precipitations and risk mitigation in European cities (2 years)
- ECHO project SAVEMEDCOASTS, assessment of economic costs linked sea level rise along the Mediterranean coasts (1 vear)
- H2020 project CLARA, climate forecast enabled knowledge services (3 years)
- ECHO project CHAKE OU, flood risk mapping in Paraguay (8 months)
- National Climate Change Adaptation Plan (PNACC) for Italy (2 years)

Contact: Jaroslav Mysiak

SKILLS

Spatial analytics

Map Design

Pvthon

LANGUAGES

Enalish Full Professional Proficiency Italian

Native Proficiency

PUBLICATIONS

Journal article

07/2021

Cost-benefit analysis of coastal flood defence measures in the North Adriatic Sea

M. Amadio, A.H. Essenfelder, S. Bagli, S. Marzi et al.

Natural Hazards and Earth System Sciences

Cost-benefit analysis of coastal flood defence infrastructures in Italy considering the effects of climate change.

Study report

2021

Investment in Disaster Risk Management in Europe makes economic sense

GFDRR, IOM

The World Bank

Reporting for DG-ECHO on Cost-Benefit analysis of existing DRM projects in the EU.

Study report

09/2021

Disasters, Conflict, and Displacement: Intersectional Risks in South Sudan

GFDRR, ECA

The World Bank

Part one: analytic mapping of intersectional risks for South Sudan based on existing data and assessments related to natural hazards and conflict and fragility.

Journal article

03/2019

Testing empirical and synthetic flood damage models: the case of Italy

M. Amadio, A.R. Scorzini, F. Carisi, A.H. Essenfelder et al.

Natural Hazards and Earth System Sciences

Study to evaluate the predictive performance of existing flood damage models in comparison with empirical losses.

EDUCATION

PhD in Science and Management of Climate Change

Ca' Foscari University

09/2015 - 12 / 2018

Venice (IT)

o Thesis title: Integrated Framework for Flood Risk Assessment in Italy. The thesis consists of four articles published on academic journals.